<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Empire Press - How Airplanes Fly</string>
    <string name="article">
        Have you ever as a child run through the wind with a paper airplane in your hand? If not, then I’ll tell you that I certainly have. And, it is one of the most fascinating things you’d ever do. I remember when once, as a child at age seven, I took a paper airplane I had made with a friend, and we both coursed into the street and skidded off, with giggles in our faces, pointing our paper airplanes straight towards the wind. \n\n
The wind blew hard at me, hard against my shirt, flapping every thread and smoothening every rumple. My face washed against the rushing breeze gliding across and around my firm face. The savour of the experience was no different for the little paper toy in my hand. It just fluttered and flapped with intensity under the gust of the wind. It wanted to fly off and away, off of my hand. And I hated it. I wanted it to remain in my hand. But the wind just coursed through the underlings of the wraps forcing the wings to alight. It was this experience that stuck with me all through my growing years, later cementing my beliefs in the mechanical principles I was taught while eventually taking courses in my aerospace program.\n\n
What causes an airplane to fly exactly, one might ask. Well, empirical data gathered from numerous experiments and the anecdote I just described, suggest that speed is the cause. More accurately, velocity is the cause rather than speed. The more speed a body accumulates, the more air resistance the body comes against. This air resistance is a good thing, because it turns out that the shape of the body when it surfaces the wind is what actually determines how the body will respond to the resistance. \n\n
Air, like liquid, is a fluid. And what fluids do is that when they encounter a body they cannot resist, they bend around it instead. This means that a wall coming at full speed directly against the wind will definitely encounter way more resistance or “drag” than a Frisbee thrown directly against the wind. Therefore, aeronautic scientists have over the years used the study of fluid dynamics to discover surfaces that respond the most favourably to drag. Hence, the airplane wing was invented.\n\n
For the airplane to be lifted, we have ascertained that aircraft speed must be abundant. In fact, it turns out that airplanes have over the years amassed a wide range of technologies that can be used to generate massive speed. The one currently in use is known as the aircraft engine, a fan-like drum under the wing, which works on the mechanical principle of thrust. In thrust, the engine\'s propeller is specially crafted such that each of its blades has a design structure that specifically pushes or pulls any fluid forward or backward, depending on counter-clockwise or clockwise spin. \n\n
When the propeller is rotated multiple times, then air starts to blow to the back of the engine. The engine uses piston and other thermodynamic engine principles to ensure that more air pressure and thus force is instantaneously generated at the back of the engine in comparison to the front. The aircraft will therefore have much less instantaneous force at the front than it has at the back. The result is velocity or speed forward.\n\n
The rotation of the propeller is provided by fuelled piston cylinders which directly engage and disengage with internal rotary magnets, thereby creating a plethora of revolutions per minute, as regularly taught in the electromagnetic principle. \n\n
At this point, we have an airplane which can move at any defined speed and lift up into the air due to its shape. However, how do we know the speed at which the aircraft will be able to generate lift? Well, it turns out there was a Swiss mathematician named Daniel Bernoulli who came up with a pressure-based equation that relates speed of a fluid to the amount of pressure generated by the moving fluid. With some modifications to his amazing principle, it became easier to computerize the engine speed needed to overcome the aircraft’s weight.\n\n
Okay, so now the aircraft is in the air. How do we make sure that the aircraft always remains in the air? Well, the answer is simple. The aircraft just needs to keep generating the right amount of thrust to keep it at its instantaneously-calculated needed velocity, thus providing enough pressure for the air to always take care of the lift.\n\n
And this is how an aircraft works, at least intuitively.\n\n\n\n
    </string>
</resources>
